Finding Aid for St. Paul United Church of Christ (Lansing, Mich.) Records 1886-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Paul United Church of Christ (Lansing, Mich.) records 1886-1998, 1940-1998
St. Paul United Church of Christ (Lansing, Mich.)
1 oversize folder
6.3 linear feet
Church in Lansing, Michigan, founded in 1886 and dissolved in 1998. Record group includes the following series: history, membership, property, administration, bulletins and newsletters, women's organizations, Sunday School, and photographs.
9920 Ba/2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by St. Paul United Church of Christ in September 1998. Donor no. 8773
The record group is open for research.
The German Evangelical St. Paul Church was founded in 1886 by Reverend C.C. Haag and sixteen founding families, led by G. Almendinger, Martin Gassenmeier, Christ Guenther, Joseph Hoffman, Ludwig Jungkind, Philip Kainoth, Charles Piella, Ulrich Rosli, Fred Schubel, Johann Schwarz, Philipp Seyfried, Felix Siegrist, Henry Siegrist, Dr. Charles Ultes, Julius Karl Wolf, and Gottlieb Ziegler. (The spelling of names changed over the years; these spellings were taken from the first bound volume of the church's constitution and records.) The young Reverend Haag and his wife had been called from Germany to America by the Michigan District of the Evangelical Synod of North America as a response to the interest shown by these families to begin another German church in the Lansing area.
The first services were held on September 12, 1886, in a church rented from the English Church Society. St. Paul's was officially founded on October 17, 1886. With Rev. Haag also conducting services in Charlotte and Grand Ledge, his wife assumed leadership of the Sunday School class of fifteen children and also started the Ladies Aid Society for the women of the church.
In 1888, under the leadership of Reverend F. Macer, St. Paul Church purchased land at the corner of Genesee and Walnut Streets, on which they built a frame church and parsonage. Nineteen years later, with the congregation led by Reverend E.H. Spathelf, these buildings were sold and moved, and St. Paul Church built the current brick building, completed in 1908. By 1909 contributing membership had increased to 55 people, and a 17-member choir was formed. By 1936, contributing membership had increased even further to 250 people. Church records were kept in German until circa 1920, and services were still conducted in German until around 1930.
The St. Paul's Missionary Society was started by women of the church in 1926 to conduct mission work "in Christian service to the local church community, Evangelical Synod, and the Kingdom at large." In 1930 the Tabitha Society was formed as a community service and fund-raising group for the church. (This group later became the Women's Fellowship in the 1940s.)
1934 saw the merger of the Evangelical Synod and the Reformed Church in the United States, and the church's name was subsequently changed to St. Paul Evangelical and Reformed Church.
In 1954, the church purchased the lot adjacent to the church and razed the apartment house on it, which had been previously gutted by fire. The following year the empty lot was used to build a "New Wing" on the church for a choir rehearsal room, robe storage, meeting space, kitchenette, furnace room and Sunday School rooms. The addition was dedicated on October 30, 1955.
In 1961 another merger took place. The church was renamed St. Paul United Church of Christ after the joining of the Evangelical and Reformed Church with the Congregational Christian Church.
A fire in the spring of 1978 caused heavy smoke damage to the building and destroyed many of the church's historical records. Throughout the years the church celebrated its major anniversaries with celebrations, and for its centennial celebration, the mayor of Lansing declared October 19, 1986, "St. Paul United Church of Christ Day."
St. Paul Church shared its building and facilities with a number of various new churches and organizations in the 1990s, including St. Stephen's Community Church (1992-1993), Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (1996); and the Church in the City, hosted by The Mount Hope Church (1997-1998). They also shared their facilities with the Michigan Dyslexia Institute, Horizons (divorce counseling) and Harvest House Children at Risk.
The church struggled to continue in the 1980s and 1990s for a variety of reasons. The congregation fought continually through planning, fund-raising, efforts to increase membership and votes to remain in operation as an individual church. On January 11, 1998, however, the congregation voted to dissolve, and the last service was held by Reverend Douglas Asamoa on April 19, 1998.
The records of St. Paul United Church of Christ in Lansing, MI, consist of 6.2 linear feet and 1 oversize folder. The materials consist of administrative materials, publications, records of historic events, and several bound volumes of historic materials, including the church's constitution, council meeting minutes, meeting minutes and activities of various women's organizations, and photographs. Bound volumes through c.1920 are in German, reflecting the ethnic origins of the church. The records are arranged into eight series: History, Membership, Property, Administration, Bulletins and Newsletters, Women's Organizations, Sunday School, and Photographs. These materials reflect the evolution of the St. Paul's from a small, German church at the end of the 19th century into an urban church at the end of the 20th century. We know from historic accounts by members and from newsletters that a fire in 1978 destroyed some of the church's records, but there does not appear to be any documentation in the collection that details which records were destroyed.
Pastors of St. Paul United Church of Christ
1886-1888 C.C. Haag
1888-1889 F. Macer
1890-1890 Paul Grob
1890-1894 C. Spathelf
1896-1896 L. Gross
1898-1899 J. Lindenmeyer
1899-1903 C. Zimmerman
1903-1908 E.H. Spathelf
1908-1911 P. Gehle
1911-1917 E.F. Lawrenz
1919-1920 Edwin F. Macer
1920-1922 B.E. Schalow
1922-1928 G.E. Krause
1928-1940 Alfred P. Hardt
1941-1941 Wm. Carpenter
1941-1949 Frank Rupnow
1950-1953 Robert Baumann
1954-1963 R.E. Eshmeyer
1964-1966 David R. Fisher
1966-1978 Claude Kelley
1978-1981 Theodor Tuenge
1981-1990 Roger Stutesman
1990-1991 D. Wenstrom
1991-1993 Rose Hermonat
1993-1994 Ann Slade
1994-1994 Melodee Smith
1994-1998 Douglas Asamoa
Subjects:
St. Paul United Church of Christ (Lansing, Mich.); Lansing (Mich.)--Church history.
Subjects - Visual Material:
St. Paul United Church of Christ (Lansing, Mich.); Lansing (Mich.)--Churches.; Churches--Michigan--Lansing.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- History
  The History series was pulled together from disparate files in the collection to give an overview of the church's evolution and to highlight special events and turning points in its history. It comprises .4 linear feet and includes both folders of loose materials, including various versions of the Constitution and By-Laws, and bound volumes of church records, including early baptisms, marriages, confirmations, burials, and a speech given at the 40th anniversary celebration.
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1)
  - Special Events (Box 1)
  - Publicity (Box 1)
  - Dissolution (Box 1)
  - Bound records 1886-1903 (Box 1)
  - Bound records 1904-1953 (Box 1)
  - Eickorn, Phil-40th Anniversary speech 1926 (Box 1)
- Membership
  The Membership series comprises .3 linear feet and documents the congregation as a whole, as well as events in the lives of individual members. This series contains individual records of baptisms, confirmations, marriages, deaths, transfers to other congregations, and conditional membership (unlike the bound records included in the History series). It also includes membership directories.
  - Baptisms (Box 1)
  - Confirmations (Box 1)
  - Marriages
    - 1946-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1978 (Box 1)
  - Deaths 1966-1994 (Box 1)
  - Directories (Box 1)
  - Transfers (Box 1)
  - Conditional (Box 1)
- Property
  The Property series was pulled together from various files in the collection. It comprises .2 linear feet and details individual projects, proposals, space-sharing with other churches and organizations, and documents regarding the property, buildings and upkeep.
  - Jerico Walls (Box 1)
  - Relocation Study 1965 (Box 1)
  - Mayflower Merger Study (Box 1)
  - St. Stephen's (United Church of Christ) (Box 1)
  - Michigan Dyslexia Institute (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Administration
  The Administration series is one of the most extensive series in the collection. It comprises 1.1 linear feet. The first subseries are two bound volumes which include the Constitution and Council minutes from 1909-1936. The third volume in the series is a bound ledger of financial transactions from 1907-1913. The foldered 1946-1998 Yearly Files that follow include Council meeting minutes, Annual Reports, Treasurer's Reports, Pastor's Reports, administrative correspondence between the Council and other organizations within the church, and correspondence with organizations outside the church. As a whole this series recounts the monthly and annual goings-on of the church, its evolution over ninety years, the organized effort to run the church smoothly, and the ties among Council members and between the Council and other organizations.
  - Council Minutes 1909-1927 (Box 1)
  - Council Minutes 1927-1936 (Box 1)
  - Collections Ledger 1907-1913 (Box 1)
  - Yearly Files 1946-1962, 1966-1998, 18 folders (Box 2)
- Bulletins and Newsletters
  - Combined
    The Bulletins and Newsletters series comprises 2.3 linear feet and includes almost all regular publications produced by St. Paul's from 1946 until its close in 1998. In their original order, bulletins and newsletters were sometimes kept together and sometimes separated; this order is reflected in the current organization. The bulletins detail the hymns, readings, sermon topics and responses for each weekly worship service, as well as meeting notices and upcoming events. The newsletters, published monthly, include messages from the pastor, notices or schedules of upcoming events, announcements of births, birthdays, weddings, anniversaries and deaths, general church-related news items, timely items of interest, and humorous cartoons.
    - 1940, 1943-1954, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1956-1963, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Bulletins
    - 1955 (Box 3)
    - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1966-1977, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - 1988-1992, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1994 (Box 4)
    - Lenten 1969-1977 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    - 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - 1971-1978, 1981, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1988-1998, 4 folders (Box 5)
- Women's Organizations
  The series of Women's Organizations includes the histories and administration of the Ladies Aid, Tabitha, Missionary Society, Women's Guild, and Koinonia groups of the church. It comprises 1.7 linear feet. The majority of these documents are in bound journals, including the Ladies Aid constitution and early meeting minutes in German. The remaining foldered materials were removed from the bound journals and collected from files. These records recount the generous nature of the women of the church and their numerous contributions to local and international causes, fund-raising efforts for St. Paul's, and caregiving to church members in need.
  - Ladies Aid
    - Loose Papers (Box 5)
    - Yearly Files 1904-1952, 1963-1975, 5 volumes (Box 5)
    - Financial Ledger 1926-1965 (Box 5)
  - Tabitha
    - Loose Papers (Box 6)
    - Yearly Files 1913-1930, 4 volumes (Box 6)
    - Band 1 1926-1931, 1942-1954, 4 volumes (Box 6)
    - Band 3 1952-1954 (Box 6)
    - Afternoon Circle 1955-1960 (Box 6)
  - Missionary Society
    - Loose Papers (Box 6)
    - Yearly Files 1915-1965, 7 volumes (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Koinonia 1965 (Box 6)
    - Women's Guild and Fellowships 1964-1976 (Box 6)
- Sunday School
  The Sunday School series is comprised of .2 linear feet of bound volumes. These records detail the meetings of the Sunday School teaching staff (1933-1942) and financial accounts (1950-1989). The meetings outline regular issues such as finances, book and supply purchases, children's programs, birthday cards, teacher/class pairings, gift-giving, and upcoming meetings and events.
  - Yearly Files 1933-1942, 2 volumes (Box 7)
  - Financial Ledger 1950-1989 (Box 7)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series comprises .1 linear feet and has been separated into two subseries of Buildings & Pastors and Events & Members, respectively. Few dates were available, but photograph types include black & white, color, 35mm, and Polaroid. Included in the Buildings & Pastors subseries are photos of the original wood-frame building and the more recent brick building, interior photos of the worship area, fellowship area, organ, stained glass windows, and various ministers, including Revs. Eshmeyer, Stutesman, and Kelley. Members & Events includes wedding and confirmation photos, church picnic, and candid and posed photos of individual members and/or families.
  - Buildings and Pastors (Box 7)
  - Events and Members (Box 7)